Hope you...a good lunch break.
Thank you for coming to this talk on digital linking my name is
...money in and I'm a lead program manager on the windows input platform team.
In today's talk I'm going to discuss how digital pen is a powerful tool for
creativity and productivity and how you can incorporate inc
in your windows synapse differentiate the app experience and delight your users?
Then I'll talk.
About the new inc platform in windows ten and how easy...
To use to enable you to enableto incorporating in your apps.
Before we get started have been us to remind you to fill
evaluation form a at the end...this talk at the end of this the cure
...will once again be displayed at the end.
We humans have been.
Using our hands to express ourselves visually and communicate
for very long time.
From the early cave painters of the analytic...to the development of the egyptian
hire of lives and...description around three thousand bc humans are used
...like implements to communicate and right.
By contrast
we have been using the keyboard amounts for a very short time in our
evolutionary history the typewriter and keyboard where only invented in the nineteenth-century.
And, mouse and keyboard on a computer is much
more recent the most only shipped in nineteen eighty three with the microsoft mouse.
So, given hour-long history with
...by hand it's much more natural for us to use append.
I mice of use a lot of different devices at home and network.
Even so I bring a pen and...notebook with me to my meetings where...work.
And, this is much more convenient and immediate for me rather than pulling
out my laptop logging in and then typing away noisily with my keyboard.
I find myself that listening better with a pen in hand rather than looking at the screen.
And, according to several studies I retain information better too.
I'm sure this is the case with many of you as well.
We use the
pen as a powerful tool to express ourselves faster.
More freely and in a more personal way.
many activities on this picture our best expressed with pen and paper
whether it is dueling brainstorming ideas...
...us express ourselves visually when words are not effective.
Each time to bring these experiences into the digital devices and the apps we are building.
I believe that digital linking is
the next frontier for human creativity and productivity.
Imagine what we could do if we could make
inkling on devices as easy as pen and paper but also
hardness the our of the computer to do things we couldn't do on pen and paper.
This opens up several new possibilities.
As input comes in from a digital pen we can leave it as inc.
As far as that pc
and the devices concern inc is a trail of the tools motion.
And, the data it represents can
be all kinds of things from writing to sketches.
To just plain strokes.
And, if we do this well it matches the experience on pen and paper.
A site...here since I get this question asked
a lot what's the difference between a pen and a stylists.
Append like this is append like the chips on
surface three is the position device it actively communicates with the device.
It is grated capturing details that's got buttons for additional functionality like the
...button at the end of it here and then a button in the
back for apps to get launched on the start screen, for example.
As...like this.
At the tip of a...just a soft...and it's just a finger replacement.
It is just a stick and not a precision tool.
So, once we capture the inc strokes.
And, get depend on paper experience with just inc drawing.
We have the ability to do put things certain things more easily since we are in the digital domain.
The ability to change the color of the inc after the fact.
Or be able to highlight overlaying and also because it's
the digital medium...can mix inc with other content in our documents
inc with text and images so on so forth.
We can go further with
...by analyzing the inc data and using the...
to do things like search I cannot do this with my physical notebook.
Of course I can go a bit further and convert the digital
...into text or shapes this.
Is useful and delightful experience for a number of situations either
...a writing app or in a sketching out?
To explore this further.
Let's look at a couple of scenario...to see how
...can be used to enhance existing apps these are scenario concepts
and not actual products but these ideas can
help us explore out how winking get add a different dimension to an existing app.
Take the maps up this is something we haw we all have on
or devices and we that we k around in our pockets are in our bags.
The map control itself is also available for use in many of the apps that...building.
Imagine invocation or a business trip.
My typical the typical thing that I do is go down to the
concierge desk and ask for directions to a restaurant art...to go to.
imagine if instead of the concierge pulling out a paper map and marking up with
...paper up
paper the pen or pencil if they could market up on a digital device.
And, it's much more convenient for me to then carry...device around.
But, since is a digital device.
It opens up several new possibilities.
With the digital map I can...in much more easily and
see more details when I get closer to my destination.
Of course because it's a digital app I can
rotated or share the map itself with the annotation.
Why...or messaging with other people that I...meeting?
And, of course the app can go one step further by enriching the experience you by integrating it with the
comp us...the gps...and provide me with turn by turn directions.
So, the digital inc ads
a totally new dimension to this scenario and the app experience.
Email is another scenario where.
I can use may...right much more naturally with inc and add some personality to my messages.
Of course if I want ascended the traditional way.
Because it's digital I can go ahead and converted to text.
And, send a message...just like I would in this case thinking became a medium
...became a more convenient waveform into input the message.
Of course...think I can go to the next step.
underline the words of interest with my plan or imagine circling words drawing
and arrow or doing any number of things we tend to
do naturally to draw attention to a particular portion the message to the audience.
Of course these scenarios have existed for some time.
Microsoft pioneer the tablet pc platform.
More than a decade ago and...
supported these types of apps and some of these avce are still shipping with these experiences.
One of the problems was
the availability of hardware devices the hardware devices that supported
...were expensive and heavy.
The good news is that hardware is catching up.
Over the last few years many in a
way to windows hardware devices like the surface pro three.
Have become available that do a great job of supporting...
The chart on this slide shows the incredible growth of these devices in the market.
Over the last three
years we've seen a fifty percent year over year growth of devices that support...
today there are more than fifty million devices ready to running...
And, give users the best experience with...linking.
So, what makes a good?
Thinking experience.
When we started working on windows ten we asked of the question?
How can we make
digital linking rival the intimacy and simplicity of writing with depend on paper?
I believe there are two requirements for delightful digital linking experience.
First the inc that is
...on the screen needs to look beautiful it needs to capture
the nuances of your handwriting or drawing taking into account things like pressure.
It also needs to feel like inc flows from the tip of the...
With a ball point...there is never lag between...inc.
Second using the...should be comfortable and inspire confidence.
All the...a different way and we should be able to draw with
the natural posture.
Both of these things represent a challenge today which we needed to solve to delight
our users.
Are going to each of these aspects in a little more detail?
When we write on paper...
deposited continuously and we see every detail as intended?
Are ice are very good at perceiving those details?
The amount of details
are the resolution that we can proceed with our ice varies with the distance.
For healthier result at...average reading additions of one-fourth.
Which is where we typically read when we are reading stuff on-screen the maximum resolution we
can perceive is seven hundred-twenty dpi or ppi pixels branch?
The publishing industry has known this for some time because this is
resolution at which high-end magazines are printed to deliver superior readability.
The high-resolution displays on today's devices is around three in
But, some of the premium devices are starting to rival.
Paper in terms of resolution how do we make sure inc does the same thing.
When I put the pen down on a digital device there is a touching
...grid on the display
called the iq layer that detects the position and the movement of the
pen and reported to the os at a certain resolution and rate?
So, rather than a continuous inc strokes in the
analog medium the oversees a series of discrete points that
...process and rendering strokes.
Also been rewrite or drawl.
Our hands weighty pressure depending on what we are doing we tend to do it
intuitively...without even realizing we are doing it.
For example, when I write english text?
I notice that I tend to reduce the pressure at the end of a stroke.
In order to render beautiful inc we
have to effectively fit the points that we get from the sensor into a
smoot curve and inc things like pressure to drawer realistic looking inc.
The good news is that we have taken care of this in the new platform with windows
...let me show you a demo.
To give you an idea of what we have done with beautiful inc.
Switching to a demo machine here.
First I want to show you.
...existing.
Using windows eight api
...implemented linking to give you an idea of what's the problem we're trying to solve
...slightly so when I market with my pen here notice what happens
is just the strokes certainly changed when I left depend...more crime.
So, what's happening here is that the
inc data comes in as discrete points.
The stroke is constructed by connecting them.
Astros come in and then when I lift the ban the entire curve is processed
...and redundant so that creates
...subtle shift that are...can see very easily?
Some applications are worked around this by doing
their own rendering with lot more processing and writing lots of code.
But, there is typically there is some tradeoff, tradeoff in terms...or performance.
Office one node is one of the apps that I've done this.
So, here I have attest app that.
That I have inc office rendering and then I'll also show you how the new platform is doing
it so the office styling king.
When I draw the strokes there was no change in this stroke it...
...also notice that it took into account pressure so the
...stroke is thinner at the end of it.
But, even though this looks more at the normal resolution when I zoom in you can see
...is there is still a series of discrete
...line segments that are connected so it's not perfectly smooth
...certain types of curves arise can still see it.
So, we decided to address this as well as address the memory and performance
...considerations in the new platform.
...switch to the new render.
And, show the same thing.
So, here when I draw.
Drew similar curve.
Now when I zoom in.
You'll notice that.
It is perfectly...
Even when I zoom in.
Quite a bit can keep going here.
Also notice that at the end of the stroke.
The pressure from this from the spend...spend by the way can support two-hundred-and-fifty six levels
of pressure is captured so the inc looks much more natural and pleasing to the I.
Once we have achieved this default level of smoothness and
the beauty with the inc we can go further more to beautifully inc.
I can of course very.
The thickness of the pen.
And, this is useful for languages...rating is much more prevalent like hindi,
for example.
Directing can supports not just
...the with but also other aspects of it like the aspect
ratio and rotation so you draw a few more things here.
So, when I change the aspect ratio and
rotation can notice that we can bring...writing to life?
And, this rendering is happening on-the-fly and it's as you can see
...really fast because all incurring in
windows ten is done using the gpu on direct textual.
The other aspect of this challenges to make sure digital...follows.
The user spend as well as spend on paper any lag between the pen
and ink is perceived by the user latency.
Today with the typical windows
...like the...that I showed you there is a presumable
latency of anywhere between eighty two hundred milliseconds on current devices.
There are three things that causes, causes latency.
First is the...hardware latency this is the time between when the depend hardware
itself.
...time...takes depend hardware to report the data to the os.
The second thing that causes
agencies the processing of that input and rendering by the os and the app and finally there is
some latency on the output side this is the time when the
...rendered and its...to be displayed and then there is a small amount of latency in the
displace system itself to...the pixels that the user sees.
With the work we're doing...windows ten we are.
We are working hardware address this latency end-to-end.
Through user research we have determined...the average writing speed.
Most users feel that inkling fields on par with
...on paper if the system is able to deliver an into and latency of fifty milliseconds.
We are confident of achieving this with the current hardware on windows ten.
And, we are working very closely with our hardware partners to reduce the
latency further in the next generation devices.
...a quick video to illustrate this has been captured the high-speed camera the top
Is showing inc rendering on a current windows eight application
and the bottom pain is rendering the same thing with windows...ten nap desktop?
And, as...as a draws here.
The gap between the pen and the.
The gap between the pen and the inc
...inks trail on the topping.
Is quite a bit in windows say then we have reduced by almost fifty percent in windows
And, with the next generation hardware we are hoping to reduce it even more.
I mentioned that earlier for a great thinking experience using
...should be comfortable and inspire confidence.
We all...the...differently majority of us are
...statistically.
But, a good percentage of us are also left-handed and even within these two major groups
there are variations in how we hold the...as you can...these pictures.
I myself all the pen such a resource that my
...is trailing training my hand.
But, I feel like no matter how you hold the...visual ensure that writing fields natural.
For the user to field confident the system should not leaves
trademarks from the...in my case all the knuckles of the site of the hand.
The system should not be...zooming of the content because the surface supports both
...pending touch manipulation and pending.
These are things that users
experience today and we are improving the experience with the new...platform.
So, let's talk about the new platform windows ten we are introducing a new
inkling platform build from the ground-up called directing.
It is designed to handle
...input and ingrained...efficiently for your apps.
We are doing work in the windows
input infrastructure to bring input support inc support
to windows phone and other mobile devices running windows for the first-time.
This means that users can inc even on devices that only support
touch like most of the forms that we carry around.
The platform takes care of rendering beautiful
link with low into and latency like you saw in the demo.
Directing models the...pressure to create realistic inc with smoot curves and we
render those curves using a fast busy algorithm.
On the gpu using direct...
The platform optimizes the inc input processing and rendering infrastructure
to reduce the end-to-end latency.
As you saw in the video we are making great progress here.
I encourage you to come up come up later and...out
on my device because doing it's hard to capture that on video but,
it's easier to...of our by yourself.
Next we are improving the user experience with thinking with direct
think apps users are able to comfortably
...palms by linking...the confidence that the
...willing and that palmer finger won't...unexpected things to happen.
Finally we want to make it easy for you to add
inks scenarios in your apps.
Our goal was that it should be possible to implement a default
level of functionality.
With just a few lines of code.
At the same time we want to provide the rich set of api is
to provide flexibility in our in your applications.
Here's a high-level view of the inc platform with each level
representing additional levels of functionality flexibility and our.
Example control and this is your entry point for
thinking in windows time makes it really easy for you to add
...functionality your apps we'll see this in a moment.
The inc presenter gives you the next level functionality to do more with
inc enable you to configure different aspects of inc.
Input handling and rendering.
Windows has always been about giving developers more
our and flexibility if they needed so if you have that need and
...to can have find control over inc input processing are implement
advanced scenarios...recognition the api scalable and powerful for that.
Let's take a look at in canvas encoder.
...a simple example application and it's
already set up with some simple you can see...the designer its and
...grid and some text blocks and whatnot and
...receiving and I'm going-to go ahead and adding can washear.
...so I can just with that single-line of code I have enable linking in this app and I
mean...being conan and also because in canvas collects thing
and supports erasing by default if I make a mistake I can gordon
...the strokes do it again.
And, the inc looks.
Like it did in the demo looks beautiful it took.
The expression into accountyou can see the
inc is thinner at the end of the stroke and
it's you're able to see the inc following the pen cursor.
So, I being able to do this all this with just a single line of code.
In contrast doing the same thing in windows eight.
Would have been more dozens of lines of code and involving your app doing its
own rendering and, still it may not be able to get to this level without a lot of work?
Let's get back to the...
In can was is great for enabling inc in your apps and getting the platform to do the heavy lifting
...like you saw just now.
But, in many of your apps you may want to do more configuration and customization to enable
richer scenarios.
For example,
by default in canvases configured for inkling with...only
touch input is assume to be passed on to the app for touch manipulation.
But, let's see if you want to target your...for both
...desktop and an mobile users.
And, want to enable configured for both
pen and touch to doing king in presenter as a way to do that.
All you may won't allow your users to change thing color or thickness.
Each in
can was instance as an presenter associated with this in presenter allows you to change
the default configuration it also allows you to get at the
inc stroke data and...for later use.
There are a lot more advanced customization options possible.
That give you the flexibility and our...won't have time to cover this in this talk but there
is a follow-on talk at...pm that goes into
a lot more details on harvesting the full our of digital linking with directing.
Let's go back to the...signature app that we just saw.
So, first I'm going to configure this app to support both...and touching.
So, to do that I get the inc presenter object from.
From the canvas in canvas and then I said the input device type to support
As well as touch.
So, let's go and add that code.
Next I want to wire up the clear button that we have in the designer.
To be able to clear the signature in case I got the signature
on when I run the app so because in canvas as I mentioned
...as the user re-thinking rich I can get access to them using
the stroke container and then all I have to do is clear the stroll container?
Once rocketing is...or updated in can in
the in presenter takes care of read...the content.
So, let's go and add that code.
Next I want to be able to saved...once I'm happy with the with my signature.
here I have a bunch of why deplete code in order to specify
the name of the file where I want to store it in this case I'm storing it in the pictures folder.
But, the key
api to call is the savy zinc method.
That is part of this role container so in this case this
role container ask the signature that is collected in this app and...
will go and do the work of saving it into the standard...file format?
So, let's go in and all that code.
So, now I can inc as before.
And, of course...it but because now I'm
enable both touch and pending king I can use the stylists eyesore
showed you before and I can use it to include that as well or my finger.
And, we wired up the clear to clear
...for container so I can clear the signature completely and I can
add signature submitted and it gets saved in the pictures for.
You can see that the inc is saving
the iso format the iso format is a...container and it shows to
...more than eighty being data as well as a...representation of that this
program...showing the different presentation of that of that of that data?
And, because this is a universal windows app
...I can deploy the same app to my to
my phone so I happen to have deployed that app on this phone before and.
So, let me quickly show you that.
You can see the same app working on the...
Next I would like to make you aware
...standard...control called inc toolbar.
This is the same ux control
that is implemented within the microsoft age browser for note-taking with inc.
The include what is a collection of several common tools like
high later in color picker and the
inc thickness adjustment package into a simple to use zone control
each the easiest way to provide a consistent linking to...in your app.
...toolbar control is still in beta but you can check it out through the
visual studio gallery downloadable as a free extension.
With the simple...lapped that we build the signature app show you how
...directing
and implementing king in a typical enterprise type scenario.
Blinking is not just about static content we can imagining
we can imagine doing the same thing with other types of content video,
for example, we so we built a simple.
Video
annotation test app to try it out so let me show you that.
So, here is a simple...lap that opens...video and.
And, this app comes with typical vcr controls but what I can do is.
And, market up.
Keep playing the video some more.
And, these annotation stay with the video so if I were to stop the video and share it
with someone else and the plate.
The...are exactly.
Where I put them?
You can imagine that this is useful for a number of scenarios.
I can imagine a sports coach looking at the videos of the last we
explain a and using the video to show is team how they could have done better.
These are interesting apps.
But, today I'm really thrilled to be able to show a couple of partner apps.
Through the windows inside a programme a number of you have already started evaluating the windows ten
a api is an through the developer preview bills.
The first...I want to show you is universal windows app called
...to go from siemens that enables users to manipulate three-d content using
touch this morningguggenheim or showed it off on the surface hub running that
avp media average running on.
On surface so this app allows you to open three-d models.
And, enables you to manipulated using touch.
But, the cool thing is now I can use the
...tool and start annotating this content.
So, in this case inc makes it really easy to imagine
station where engineering diagrams...the future are reviewed using this mechanism.
The next one I want
to talk about is an app called qq from a company called ten...
That's some of you may know.
...switch the machine.
Qq is a very popular.
Popular messaging avp from china.
It has more than eight hundred-million
users world-wide and it's...deployed on all platforms.
So, qq allows users to do several things they can write.
...text message in this case I'm sending a message to my friend doing fine.
It allows the user to send some send images
seconds send a picture.
So, what concluded was looked into adding
linking to this application and
...with just a few lines of code using directing and
the in canvas they were able to enable linking seo?
So, now I'm able to use the in quite board and then
...much more personalize message to my friend...
Furthermore I can go back and use the.
...board.
Annotate that picture that I showed earlier.
And, send that over as well.
So, this is an example where.
With just a few lines of code qq was able to provide a
much more richer and personal experience to the users.
Next up is a universal windows avp from a start-up in...
called silicon vendors the app is course catch ability and I would like to
invite ryan harris
...co-founder one of the...founders to show you the app and the xp and
their experience leveraging directing please welcome ryan harris.
My name is ron harris in along with my brother miles harris we developed
...called schedule it's a sketching drawing application on
the windows store in allows you to create digital journals.
And, store your images as pages in them.
When we set out to develop schedule we wanted to make?
The...most powerful mobile sketching application any platform we also want to find
a useful place in a creators workflow.
To do that we had to beat.
Traditional mediums and
other mobile applications so we started looking at the creative process
we noticed one thing that despite the user skill
level whether they were a professional artist or really struggle to express themselves
visually they always use the tool...a pencil
a brush something to help them express themselves so to limit an
applications
purely touch input would fail this universal standard that we all have
...this made windows
and extremely appealing developing platform for us because.
They have the active panned.
One of the key things...allows us to do is get at pressure.
So, I can very quickly and easily make a
...that varies in diameter based
on the pressure provided you can also apply this to other
settings like opacity scenario I can quickly change.
The opacity and the diameter maestro based on pressure.
Independent...much more than that because it allows me to
be more productive because it provides more natural experience
as opposed to you pending with a finger selecting putting...thing selecting I can differentiate
between my inputs with touch and stylists.
It freeze it frees me up too do more things I
can say assign a tool to touch the requires less precision...
Since the...has
a secondary button I can have a secondary tool attached to it.
So, without involving any
uri I can switch between three different tools just depending on how I interact with the
canvas it also allows me to free of charge for gestures like to
fingerprinting...zooming all-knowing love.
And, three fingered...through the enduser in reduce.
This is the kind of natural expression that we provide in
are editing mode.
We wanted to bring that into other aspects of our application we've done that through direct
So, if I go out back to our page.
A prominent feature we...the ability to name.
One of your journal pages and even our users.
Didn't know it was there because it's not as intuitive is
the rest it's kind of your classic?
Text input you push a button hold person text field launcher keyboard.
Type in your title and then it would be there so
...abilities low in the number of steps very high.
With the our of direct inc we can increase discover ability
by putting a text field in when you come within range.
It provides even as bad as my aunt my handwriting is very good
excellent handwriting recognition so in much fewer
...natural in.
Much easier to understand
flow I can get the same result...the best part of this is that
we implemented directing in less than a day.
Which is longer than the time it took us to do the traditional text input through keyboard?
It's really made is very excited about the potential for this and other features of our
application.
Thank you thank you.
I really want to thank all the three third-party partners allowed us to show
their apps they are all in the audience in addition...we have
...from qq is...team lead for qq somewhere in the audience and
...from siemens is sitting back there as well so,
thank you very much for allowing us to...the rest of the audience.
So, the...can was and inc presenter gives you an easy way
to implement creating king functionality in your app you saw several examples of that.
But, the platform as more.
As I mentioned the platform
is flexible and powerful enough for you to implement even richer scenarios.
These include
inc recognition inc editing and more.
There's a follow-on talk at
...pm to cover some of these in much more detail.
...attend to learn more about these capabilities.
Also we have a few samples and we are going to post more samples on get
hub to learn more about the directing api...
Here's a recap of what we cover today.
...is a great tool for enabling productive scenarios in your app there
are now millions of pennant touch enable devices in your customers
hands so you...app is ready to...on these devices.
Windows ten the new inc platform is built from the
ground-up to start rivaling depend on paper experience.
The smoothing demo you saw and the...in
the apps that we that I showed that you saw hopefully give you a good idea of the capabilities.
Finely
...api makes it really easy to start...king functionality in your apps.
I would like to leave you with a simple call-to-action.
Differentiate your universal windows app...thinking today we have
...a powerful platform to for-you to be able to do that.
Your customers have the devices two-run your...enabled app.
Please check out the api and...feedback.
And, directing the at the following email address directing at microsoft-dot-com.
Please submit your feedback for the session.
We have time for some questions.
And, if you run out of time I'm going to be outside to talk with you as long as you on thank
you very much for coming it's been a pleasure to talk about this.
...for this release is all for universal...
...question regarding text recognition so when you can when you perform.
Ocr I would say doesn't require any kind of connected the
...should device be online or it can be performed to-you no-fly
...as well ok, good question so
...cognition is built into the platform so it doesn't need to be
...part of the operating system so,
text recognition works with some thirty-plus languages on the desktop
and you don't every connected...online in order to have the recognition work at the
and defy pm talk there is the more detail on how to use recognition api.
Thank you.
I will one-plus so not...any plan supporting the winfrey to api.
I'm sorry I didn't get...so, we...app and implement a separate
known this functionalities available for universal windows app wintry...is something we are looking into.
...question to the eye-hand running...any improvements...made for like
japanese or chinese characters I know like windows...was very good with
...english roman characters but wasn't so good on...for languages.
I don't have anything specific to talk about in terms of improvements there but,
we can talk offline about what specific things you
are noticing and I would love to get that feedback.
All right thank you very much I'm going to be around if you have things to talk about
our more questions and then please I hope to see many of you at the jpm talk
...learn more about the advance capabilities of digital
...directing thank you.